<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc [
  <!ENTITY nbsp    "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY zwsp   "&#8203;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy   "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY wj     "&#8288;">
]>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" category="exp" docName="draft-muks-dns-nta-feed-zones-00" ipr="trust200902" submissionType="IETF" tocInclude="true" tocDepth="3" symRefs="true" sortRefs="true" version="3">
  <!-- xml2rfc v2v3 conversion 3.31.0 -->
  <front>
    <title>DNS NTA feed zones</title>
    <seriesInfo name="Internet-Draft" value="draft-muks-dns-nta-feed-zones-00"/>
    <author fullname="Mukund Sivaraman" initials="M." surname="Sivaraman">
      <organization>Banu Systems Private Limited</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>6001 Beach Road, #19-09, Golden Mile Tower</street>
          <code>199589</code>
          <country>SG</country>
        </postal>
        <email>muks@banu.com</email>
        <uri>https://banu.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Operations and Management Area</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>
    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>

      <t>This memo documents a method for expressing a list of DNS
      negative trust anchors <xref target="RFC7646"/> inside a specially
      constructed DNS zone, that validating recursive name servers and
      other DNSSEC validators may configure negative trust anchors
      from.</t>

    </abstract>

  </front>
  <middle>

    <section anchor="sec_intro">

      <name>Introduction</name>

      <t>As DNSSEC deployment increases, there are more and more
      incidents where a secure trust chain to validate a domain is not
      available due to DNSSEC validation-related issues such as those
      described in Section <xref target="RFC7646" section="1"
      sectionFormat="bare">Introduction and Motivation</xref> of <xref
      target="RFC7646" />. The concept of Negative Trust Anchors (NTA)
      <xref target="RFC7646" /> was introduced to temporarily workaround
      such DNSSEC validation issues.</t>

      <t>Use of NTAs currently requires operators to follow a range of
      requirements which many DNS validating resolver operators are
      poorly equipped to follow. There are many DNS resolver operators
      who run commercial off-the-shelf resolver implementations, e.g.,
      in the form of network appliances, but do not have the ability to
      generate, manage, and regularly re-evaluate application of NTAs on
      their own. Many DNS resolver operators typically depend on their
      software vendors to manage many aspects of DNS operation for them
      automatically.</t>

      <t>As an analogous example, many DNS resolver operators also do
      not have expertise to generate and manage DNS firewalling and
      filtering information on their own, so they make use of Response
      Policy Zones <xref target="I-D.vixie-dnsop-dns-rpz" /> to provide
      this information for their resolvers. The responsibility of
      generating the information in RPZ is delgated to one or more
      trusted 3rd-parties.</t>

      <t>This draft introduces NTA feed zones, which are specially
      formatted DNS zones that communicate lists of NTAs from their
      producers to their consumers.</t>

      <t>NTA feed zone consumer software such as validating resolvers
      and other DNSSEC validators may configure NTAs from NTA feed zones
      automatically. This draft obsoletes the text "Use of an NTA MUST
      NOT be automatic." in Section <xref target="RFC7646" section="2.1"
      sectionFormat="bare">Applicability of Negative Trust
      Anchors</xref> of <xref target="RFC7646" />. The production of NTA
      feed zones as described in <xref target="sec_producers" /> still
      requires human involvement and is not automatic, but the
      consumption of NTA feed zones at validating resolvers as described
      in <xref target="sec_consumers" /> is expected to be fully
      automatic.</t>

      <t>NTA feed zones provides managed NTAs for those operators who
      are incapable of applying and maintaining NTAs on their own, so
      that they make use of negative trust anchors which they may be
      unable to use otherwise. The use of NTA feed zones is
      OPTIONAL. Operators who wish to make use of them may do so, and
      those who wish to manage NTAs on their own do not have to use NTA
      feed zones.</t>

    </section>

    <section>

      <name>Requirements notation</name>

      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL
      NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "NOT RECOMMENDED",
      "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
      described in <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/>
      when, and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown
      here.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_nta_rrtype">

      <name>NTA RR type</name>

      <t>An NTA RRset encodes a single negative trust anchor's
      configuration in its RDATA. It is a singleton, i.e., only a single
      RR of the type may exist in an NTA RRset. The wire format of NTA
      RDATA is as follows:</t>
      
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <td>RDATA field</td>
            <td>Type</td>
            <td>Field size</td>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>DOMAIN</td>
            <td>DNS name (uncompressed)</td>
            <td>Variable</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>EXPIRY</td>
            <td>Unsigned integer</td>
            <td>64 bits (8 octets)</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

      <t>The DOMAIN field encodes the domain name of the negative trust
      anchor. It MUST be an uncompressed DNS name in <xref
      target="RFC1035"/> wire format.</t>

      <t>The EXPIRY field encodes the expiry time of the negative trust
      anchor in seconds since the Epoch, 1970-01-01 00:00:00 +0000
      (UTC). It is a 64-bit unsigned integer encoded in network byte
      order. The expiry time SHOULD NOT exceed 1 week from the current
      time per Section <xref target="RFC7646" section="4"
      sectionFormat="bare">Removal of a Negative Trust Anchor</xref> of
      <xref target="RFC7646" />.</t>

      <t>The presentation format of the NTA RDATA consists of the DOMAIN
      field in <xref target="RFC1035"/> DNS name presentation format,
      followed by the EXPIRY field in decimal representation without any
      sign symbols (e.g., the string output returned by printing the
      field's value using the <tt>"%" PRIu64</tt> format string in
      C). An example can be seen in <xref target="sec_example" />.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_nta_feed_zone">

      <name>NTA feed zone</name>

      <t>The owner name of an NTA RRset also encodes the domain name of
      the NTA relative to the NTA feed zone's origin as a matter of
      convenience for implementations to make use of. This is so that
      negative trust anchors may be queried as part of a zone's existing
      domain name tree structure. As a result, the maximum length and
      number of labels of an NTA's domain name represented in the owner
      name of an RRset within an NTA feed zone as a sub-domain of the
      zone's origin may be lower than the maximum limits permitted for
      DNS names by <xref target="RFC1035"/>. This is considered
      negligible.</t>

      <t>TBD.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_producers">

      <name>Producer requirements</name>

      <t>This section documents the requirements of a NTA feed zone's
      producer. It is limited to the content of NTA feed zones and
      does not specify how the zone is transferred to consumers.</t>

      <t>TBD.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_consumers">

      <name>Consumer requirements</name>

      <t>This section documents the requirements of a NTA feed zone's
      consumer.</t>

      <t>TBD.</t>

      <t>RRsets other than that of RR type NTA in the NTA feed zone MUST
      be ignored by the consumer.</t>

      <t>Zero or more NTA feed zones may be configured at a validating
      recursive name server or DNSSEC validator. If NTAs with identical
      domain occur among multiple NTA feed zones, it is RECOMMENDED that
      the first corresponding NTA in configured order of NTA feed zones
      be used and the remaining occurences be discarded.</t>

      <t>The requirements in <xref
      target="sec_security_considerations"/> also form a part of these
      consumer requirements.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_example">

      <name>Example NTA feed zone</name>

      <t>The following is a sample NTA feed zone. It is meant to
      configure a single NTA for the domain <tt>example.com.</tt> with
      expiry time at Mon 13 Jul 19:46:48 2026 UTC. Note that in within
      the zone, the NTA RR has the owner name
      <tt>example.com.nta1.example.net.</tt> as the name is specified
      relative to the zone's origin.</t>

      <sourcecode>
$ORIGIN nta1.example.net.
$TTL 1H
@                   SOA localhost. nta-maintainer.example.net. (
                                        1 1h 15m 30d 2h)
                    NS localhost.

example.com         NTA example.com. 1783972008
      </sourcecode>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_security_considerations">

      <name>Security considerations</name>

      <t>The security considerations in Section <xref target="RFC7646"
      section="8" sectionFormat="bare">Security Considerations</xref> of
      <xref target="RFC7646" /> apply.</t>

      <t>It is strongly RECOMMENDED that NTA feed zone consumers
      regularly establish whether the party producing the NTA feed zones
      can be trusted for their NTA feed zones' content. This has at
      least three aspects of consideration: whether the NTA
      configuration in the feed zones is correct and accurate, whether
      it is maintained to be current by the producer of the NTA feed
      zone to match current network conditions, and whether access to
      the NTA feed zone is operationally available without disruption.
      An example relationship may be that the producer is the consumer's
      DNS resolver vendor and the consumer has a legal agreement with
      that vendor and trusts that vendor.</t>

      <t>It is strongly RECOMMENDED that DNS zone transfer initiators
      (clients) of NTA feed zone consumers verify the authenticity and
      integrity of the NTA feed zone data using a mechanism such as TSIG
      <xref target="RFC8945"/>.</t>

      <t>Section <xref target="RFC7646" section="4"
      sectionFormat="bare">Removal of a Negative Trust Anchor</xref> of
      <xref target="RFC7646" /> recommends that the lifetime of any NTA
      SHOULD NOT exceed a week. When NTAs are received via NTA feed
      zones, the DNSSEC validator must ensure that any NTAs whose expiry
      time is more than 1 week from the current time are either clamped
      to 1 week from the current time or discarded.</t>

      <t>If the NTA feed zone contents become stale or expire due to any
      reason, all the configured NTAs derived from that feed zone MUST
      be unconfigured and removed as soon as the condition is
      detected.</t>

      <t>If any NTAs that existed in a previous version of the NTA feed
      zone have been deleted in a new version of the zone, such NTAs
      must be unconfigured and removed immediately after the new zone's
      contents are received by the consumer.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_iana">

      <name>IANA considerations</name>

      <t>IANA is requested to allocate the following RR types in the
      "Resource Record (RR) TYPEs" registry in the "Domain Name System
      (DNS) Parameters" registry group.</t>
      
      <table>
        <thead>
          <tr>
            <th>Type</th>
            <th>Value</th>
            <th>Meaning</th>
            <th>Reference</th>
          </tr>
        </thead>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>NTA</td>
            <td>TBD</td>
            <td>a negative trust anchor</td>
            <td>See <xref target="sec_nta_rrtype"/>.</td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>

    </section>

    <section anchor="sec_acknowledgements">

      <name>Acknowledgements</name>

      <t>The idea of transferring NTAs to validators by representing
      them as transferrable DNS zones is based on Response Policy Zones
      <xref target="I-D.vixie-dnsop-dns-rpz" />.</t>

    </section>

  </middle>
  <back>
    <references>
      <name>References</name>
      <references>
        <name>Normative references</name>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7646.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8174.xml"/>
        <xi:include href="https://bib.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.8945.xml"/>
      </references>
      <references>
        <name>Informative references</name>
        <xi:include href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/bibxml3/draft-vixie-dnsop-dns-rpz-00.xml"/>
      </references>
    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
